Guide to the Records of the Brooklyn Council for Social Planning BCMS.0039
Brooklyn Collection
- Program files, 1934-1957 [bulk 1946-1957]; 1946-1957
  - Family and child welfare, 1946-1957
    - Committee on Schools and Social Agencies: Correspondence, 1954-1956 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Courts and Social Agencies: Committee Correspondence: Family and Child Care Week, 1954-1956 (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Brooklyn committee for Day Care Week: Correspondence, 1948-1957 (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - Day Care Committee: Correspondence, 1947-1955 (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - Day Care: Subcommittee on Kindergarten in Public Schools: Correspondence, 1946-1949 (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - Family Service Committee: Subcommittee regarding the need for a shelter for homeless women: Correspondence: Report, 1954 (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - Legislature Committee: Correspondence, 1950-1952 (Box 15, Folder 11)
    - Little White House Conference on Children and Youth of Brooklyn: Correspondence, 1950-1952 (Box 15, Folder 12)
    - Little White House Conference on Children and Youth of Brooklyn: Fact Sheet (Box 15, Folder 13)
    - Little White House Conference on Children and Youth of Brooklyn: Reports (Box 15, Folder 14)
    - Little White House Conference on Children and Youth of Brooklyn: Related Organizations: Correspondence, 1951-1952 (Box 15, Folder 15)
    - Little White House Conference on Children and Youth of Brooklyn: Report, "Growing up in Brooklyn" (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Little White House Conference on Children and Youth of Brooklyn: papers given, 1951 April 24 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Little White House Conference on Children and Youth of Brooklyn: photographs, 1951 April 24 (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Little White House Conference on Children and Youth of Brooklyn: proceedings, 1951 April 24 (Box 16, Folder 4-5)
    - Steering Committee: Correspondence and Committee Reports, 1949-1957 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Group work and recreation, 1934-57 [bulk 1945-1954]
    These files clarify how instrumental BCSP was in the development, improvement and maintenance of recreational facilities in Brooklyn, and describe in detail the need for new and improved community recreational facilities and centers, public school gyms, and public programs such as summer camps and swimming pools. Included here is the correspondence of the Fort Greene-Farragut Coordinating committee, which organized recreation programs in the new Fort Greene-Farragut housing project, and correspondence of the sub-committee on the establishment of St. John's Park, at Schenectady Avenue and Bergen Street. (Also see Series 5, Brooklyn neighborhood welfare and health councils, for related material.)
    - Committee Correspondence and Reports, 1934-1940 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Committee Reports and Summaries, 1946-1948 (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - Committee Correspondence and Reports, 1950-1955 (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - Committee Correspondence and Reports, 1955-1957 (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - Committee on Student Volunteers: Reports, 1945-1949 (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - Committee on Student Volunteers: Statement on "Criteria for Agencies": Correspondence, 1949 (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - Conference, 1954 April 20 (Box 17, Folder 7)
    - East New York Teen Town Program, 1947-1951 (Box 17, Folder 8)
    - Ft. Greene – Farragut Committee: Correspondence and Reports, 1950-1952 (Box 17, Folder 9)
    - Ft. Greene – Farragut Committee: Correspondence and Reports, 1953-1954 (Box 17, Folder 10)
    - Ft Greene - Farragut Coordinating Committees: Correspondence and Reports (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Ft Greene – Farragut Recreation Committee: Correspondence and Reports, 1946-1947 (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - Ft. Greene Recreation Committee: Subcommittee on Camping: Fresh Air Find Camp Reference, 1953-1954 (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - Neighborhood Needs for Recreational Facilities: Correspondence and Memos, 1945-1948 (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - Press clippings (Box 18, Folder 5)
    - Reference Manual (Box 18, Folder 6)
    - Related Reports: "A Study of Brooklyn Girls", 1934 (Box 18, Folder 7)
    - Related Reports: "A Study of Leadership and Responsibility in Planning for Public and Voluntary Recreation Services in NYC," Welfare Council of NYC, 1946 (Box 18, Folder 8)
    - Relationship between Casework Group Work Agencies – Correspondence, 1955 (Box 18, Folder 9)
    - Subcommittee on St. John's Park Project Correspondence, 1953-1954 (Box 18, Folder 10)
    - Summer Camp Physical Examinations and Correspondence and Policies, 1947-1949 (Box 18, Folder 11)
    - Summer Day Camp – Proposed NYC Code, 1955-1956 (Box 18, Folder 12)
    - Swimming Pools – Committee on Parks Department Regulation Correspondence, 1952 (Box 18, Folder 13)
    - Teen Age Night Club – Volunteer Project, 1948 (Box 18, Folder 14)
    - Unaffiliated ("Cellar") Clubs – Subcommittee Reports, 1940-1941 (Box 18, Folder 15)
  - Health care services, 1932-1957
    This subseries provides a thorough overall review of BCSP's health care committees, including Mental Health, Family Service, Nutrition, and Medical Social Work. Correspondence with the Health Council Division, a large umbrella organization which reviewed and assessed social health and welfare committees, is some of the more significant material located here, as is committee correspondence on the need for fluoridation of drinking water and the need for a community hospital in Bedford-Stuyvesant.
    - Dental Care – Proposed and Listing Services, 1941-1953 (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - Handicapped Children – Committee Correspondence and Reports, 1952-1954 (Box 19, Folder 2)
    - Cleveland Health Museum (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - Dental Care Fluoridation: Committee Correspondence and Minutes (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - Health Council Division, General Correspondence, Reports, etc., 1951-1957 (Box 19, Folder 5)
    - Health Council Division, General Correspondence, Reports, etc., 1937-1950 (Box 19, Folder 6)
    - Health Council Division – History (Box 19, Folder 7)
    - Health Council Division – Press clippings (Box 19, Folder 8)
    - Health Show, 1948 (Box 19, Folder 9)
    - Hospitals: Committee to Look into Need for a Municipal Hospital in Bedford-Stuyvesant Area: Correspondence, 1952 (Box 19, Folder 10)
    - Hospitals: Committee to Look into Need for a Municipal Hospital in Bedford-Stuyvesant Area: Correspondence, 1953-1957 (Box 19, Folder 11)
    - Legislature Committee Correspondence and Reports, 1955-1956 (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - Medical Facilities in Brooklyn – Survey, 1932 (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - Medical Social Work: Committee Correspondence (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - Medical Social Work: Committee Meeting Minutes (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - Medical Social Work: Committee Reports (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - Medical Social Work: Joint Project with Visiting Nurse Association: Correspondence and reports (Box 20, Folder 6)
    - Medical Social Work: Joint Project with Visiting Nurse Association: Reports (Box 20, Folder 7)
    - Medical Health: Joint Family Service and Mental Hygiene Committee: Correspondence, 1953-1955 (Box 20, Folder 8)
    - Medical Health: Joint Family Service and Mental Hygiene Committee: Report "Study of services to Psychotic Patients Living in the Community", 1953 March (Box 20, Folder 9)
    - Mental Health: Workshop, "Abnormal Behavior and It's Outstanding Implication,", 1954-1955 (Box 20, Folder 10)
    - Mental Health: Workshop, "Problems and Methods in Casework Treatment of Clients with Schizophrenic Conditions", 1953 (Box 20, Folder 11)
    - Multi-Phasic Screening: Subcommittee correspondence and reports (Box 20, Folder 12)
    - Narcotics: Meetings on use of narcotics by teenage youth, 1951 (Box 20, Folder 13)
    - Nutrition: Coordinating committee, correspondence and reports, 1942-1949 (Box 20, Folder 14)
    - Nutrition: Brooklyn Nutrition Committee: Correspondence and reports, 1954-1957 (Box 20, Folder 15)
    - Planned Parenthood: Membership in Welfare and Health Council of NYC, correspondence and reports (Box 20, Folder 16)
    - The Aged: Brooklyn Staff Conference on Older Adult Programs, correspondence, 1956 (Box 20, Folder 17)
    - The Aged: Conference 37, 1955 (Box 20, Folder 18)
  - Housing, 1953-1957
    These files address Brooklyn's acute public housing situation and BCSP's role in enforcing and promoting housing legislation, including support of large housing projects. The files contain primarily committee correspondence and some press clippings.
    - Committee correspondence, 1953-1954 (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - Committee correspondence, 1955-1956 (Box 21, Folder 2)
    - Committee relationship between social agencies and housing projects, correspondence and reports, 1955-1956 (Box 21, Folder 3)
    - Conference, "Housing is your Business", 1957 October 14-15 (Box 21, Folder 4)
    - Press clippings (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Neighborhood organization, 1938-1957
    Substantial documentation on social problems and community needs is provided here. Of particular interest is the correspondence of the South-Brooklyn Coordinating Committee, which organized a neighborhood council to assess local needs, and the Williamsburg-Tompkins Park Group Leadership Project, which was active in starting a youth center in response to neighborhood gang activity. (See also Series 5 for related organizations and activities).
    - Committee correspondence and reports, 1938-1946 (Box 21, Folder 6)
    - Committee correspondence and reports, 1947-1949 (Box 21, Folder 7)
    - Neighborhood Planning Committee correspondence, 1957 (Box 21, Folder 8)
    - South Brooklyn: Coordinating committee correspondence and memos, 1952-1953 (Box 21, Folder 9)
    - South Brooklyn: Community information (Box 21, Folder 10)
    - Welfare Council of NYC reports, 1940-1948 (Box 21, Folder 11)
    - Tompkins Park Neighborhood Council: Correspondence and memos, 1947-1949 (Box 21, Folder 12)
    - Williamsburg – Tompkins Park Youth Leadership Project: General correspondence, 1945-1950 (Box 21, Folder 13)
    - Williamsburg – Tompkins Park Youth Leadership Project: Press clippings (Box 22, Folder 1)
    - Williamsburg – Tompkins Park Youth Leadership Project: Reports, 1947-1950 (Box 22, Folder 2)
    - Williamsburg – Tompkins Park Youth Leadership Project: Correspondence regarding financing project, 1946-1949 (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - Professional training, 1946-1957
    Included here are files on seminars, workshops, and a Spanish language class sponsored by BCSP to aid social workers in their professional duties, as well as on the production of "Welcome to Brooklyn: Handbook for New Workers." This publication, and its subsequent editions, is found in Series 8, publications.
    - Conference for New Workers, 1955 October 18 (Box 22, Folder 4)
    - Conference for New Workers, 1956 November 8 (Box 22, Folder 5)
    - Conference for Board Member of Social Services, 1946 (Box 22, Folder 6)
    - Handbook, "Welcome to Brooklyn – Handbook for New Workers," 1954 edition: correspondence, 1954-1955 (Box 22, Folder 7)
    - Handbook, "Welcome to Brooklyn – Handbook for New Workers," 1954 edition: maps and information on social services distribution, undated (Box 22, Folder 8)
    - Handbook, "Welcome to Brooklyn – Handbook for New Workers," revised 1955 edition: Correspondence, undated (Box 22, Folder 9)
    - Handbook, "Welcome to Brooklyn – Handbook for New Workers," 1954 edition: questionnaire on the need for such a publication, undated (Box 22, Folder 10)
    - Handbook, "All about Brooklyn", 1957 (Box 22, Folder 11)
    - Spanish Language Class for Health and Welfare Workers, 1954 (Box 22, Folder 12)
    - Workshop for Teachers on Social Service Issue, 1948-1955 (Box 22, Folder 13)
  - Other programs, 1940-56 [bulk 1945-1955]
    This subseries includes files on various BCSP programs including: "Our Expanding Negro Population," a 1940 BCSP conference; a 1954 survey and statement on proposed cuts to mass transportation; World War II era veterans' services; volunteerism; and youth activities. Files include committee correspondence, reports, and pamphlets.
    - African Americans: Conference, "Our Expanding Negro Population", 1940 April 6 (Box 23, Folder 1)
    - Transportation: Survey and Statement on Proposed Service Cuts, 1954 (Box 23, Folder 2)
    - Veterans' Services: Committee reports, publications (Box 23, Folder 3)
    - Veterans' Services: Committee correspondence and membership lists, 1945-1947 (Box 23, Folder 4)
    - Veterans' Services: Manhattan Beach Housing Project, 1947 (Box 23, Folder 5)
    - Volunteers: Steering Committee Correspondence, 1954-1955 (Box 23, Folder 6)
    - Volunteers: General Correspondence, 1948-1952 (Box 23, Folder 7)
    - Youth Services: Youth Activities Committee reports, 1943-1948 (Box 23, Folder 8)
    - Youth Services: Youth Council's Project correspondence and reports, 1948-1956 (Box 23, Folder 9)
- Related welfare and health councils, 1932-57 [bulk 1946-1957]; 1946-1957
  - Welfare and Health Council of New York City, 1932-57 [bulk 1948-1957]; 1948-1957
    Alphabetical by topic; correspondence arranged chronologically.
    BCSP was a member of the city-wide Welfare and Health Council of New York; it acted as the Brooklyn borough representative agency. Formed by the merger of the Welfare Council of New York City and the Health Council of New York City in 1952, the organization disbanded itself in February 1956 and formed the Greater New York Community Council, Inc. This was done in an effort to appeal to the Catholic agencies which withdrew from the Welfare and Health Council in 1953 in protest over the admission to the Council of an arm of Planned Parenthood; the Welfare and Health Council experienced financial difficulties after this withdrawal. The Councils' primary functions were the overall planning and coordination of health and welfare services, and providing central services required by the community and the agencies city-wide to produce these services. This subseries includes committee correspondence, reports, minutes of meetings, press clippings, and related material addressing topics such as housing, services to adolescent children, mental health, services to the aged, and population. The department and committee structure of this organization corresponded closely with that of BCSP, and BCSP participated in its committee work. BCSP was dependent on the Welfare and Health Council, and its successor, the Greater New York Community Council, for the bulk of its funding. As of December 31, 1956, the Council stopped funding BCSP and the other borough councils, and they disbanded. (See Series 2, financial files for funding; see subseries 4.2 for other borough councils.)
    - Health Council of New York (Box 24, Folder 1)
    - Conference on Correctional and Allied Services, 1950 July (Box 24, Folder 2)
    - Report, "Planning for Brooklyn Children Needing Foster Care", 1936 December (Box 24, Folder 3)
    - Report, "Study of Financing of Social Work", 1932 (Box 24, Folder 4)
    - "The Known Extent of Physical Disability in NYC", 1947 (Box 24, Folder 5)
    - Annual Reports, 1953-1954 (Box 24, Folder 6)
    - Central Volunteer Bureau (Box 24, Folder 7)
    - Child Welfare Division, minutes and reports (Box 24, Folder 8)
    - Committee on Housing (Box 24, Folder 9)
    - Committee of Research Representatives of Municipal Departments, 1955 (Box 24, Folder 10)
    - Committee on Services for Adolescent Children and Youth (Box 24, Folder 11)
    - Division on Families and Adults, minutes and reports (Box 24, Folder 12)
    - Division on Families and Adults, reports on casework (Box 24, Folder 13)
    - Division of Welfare of the Aged (Box 24, Folder 14)
    - Division of Welfare of the Aged, reports and minutes (Box 24, Folder 15)
    - Group work and Recreation Division (Box 25, Folder 1)
    - Health Division: Correspondence and reports (Box 25, Folder 2)
    - Health Division: Minutes (Box 25, Folder 3)
    - Health Division: School Health (Box 25, Folder 4)
    - Legislative Policy (Box 25, Folder 5)
    - Mental Health Committee (Box 25, Folder 6)
    - Miscellaneous reports and minutes (Box 25, Folder 7)
    - Rehabilitation and Guidance Division (Box 25, Folder 8)
    - Relationship with BCSP, correspondence, 1949-1956 (Box 25, Folder 9)
    - Research Department reports (Box 25, Folder 10)
    - Services to the Aged (Box 25, Folder 11)
    - Statement on Population and Economic Projections for NYC, 1950-1970 (Box 25, Folder 12)
    - Community Council of Greater NY: Correspondence, minutes, etc., 1955-1957 (Box 25, Folder 13)
    - Community Council of Greater NY: Founding, constitution, by-laws, 1955-1956 (Box 25, Folder 14)
    - Community Council of Greater NY: Report, "Salaries in Voluntary Welfare and Health Agencies", 1957 (Box 25, Folder 15)
  - New York City regional councils, 1951-1955
    Alphabetical by council name.
    This subseries includes correspondence with and information about BCSP's sister agencies in other boroughs, including: Bronx Welfare and Health Council; Community Welfare Council of Staten Island; Queensboro Council for Social Welfare; and several Manhattan neighborhood community councils. This decentralization through regional councils helped to improve the overall effectiveness and efficiency of health and welfare planning in New York City. Files include some correspondence with these agencies about mutual concerns, as well as newsletters, reports, and related material.
    - Association of Borough Councils: Correspondence, 1956-1957 (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - Bronx Welfare and Health Council: Correspondence (Box 26, Folder 2)
    - Bronx Welfare and Health Council: Newsletters (Box 26, Folder 3)
    - Bronx Welfare and Health Council: Reports (Box 26, Folder 4)
    - Central Harlem Council for Community Planning (Box 26, Folder 5)
    - Central Harlem Street Clubs Project (Box 26, Folder 6)
    - Community Welfare Council of Staten Island (Box 26, Folder 7)
    - East Harlem Council for Community Planning (Box 26, Folder 8)
    - Manhattan Council for Social Planning (Box 26, Folder 9)
    - Queensboro Council for Social Welfare: Publications and Miscellaneous (Box 26, Folder 10)
    - Queensboro Council for Social Welfare: Newsletter, 1952-1955 (Box 26, Folder 11)
    - Yorkville Civic Council (Box 26, Folder 12)
  - Councils in other cities, 1946-1957
    Alphabetical by city.
    This very miscellaneous grouping of files contains general information on similar organizations in other American cities including: Boston, United Community Services of Metropolitan Boston; Cincinnati, Council of Social Agencies; Los Angeles, Department of Recreation and Parks; Philadelphia, Health and Welfare Council and the University of Pennsylvania School of Social Work; and Pittsburgh, Health and Welfare Federation of Allegheny County. Files contain primarily pamphlets issued by these organizations.
    - Boston: United Community Services of Metropolitan Boston, Greater Boston Community Council (Box 27, Folder 1)
    - Cincinnati: Council of Social Agencies (Box 27, Folder 2)
    - Los Angeles: Department of Recreation and Parks (Box 27, Folder 3)
    - Philadelphia: Health and Welfare Council (Box 27, Folder 4)
    - Philadelphia: University of Pennsylvania School of Social Work (Box 27, Folder 5)
    - Pittsburgh: Health and Welfare Federation of Allegheny County (Box 27, Folder 6)
- Brooklyn welfare and health councils, 1931-1957
  - Neighborhood councils, general information, 1931-54 [bulk 1950-1954]
    Alphabetical by folder title.
    These files include general information and correspondence regarding the overall coordination of local neighborhood councils by BCSP, as well as chronicling the debate about the administrative hierarchy of the various welfare and health councils in New York City and in Brooklyn. Also included here are publications from other cities on the concept of neighborhood councils, and reports and statistics on Brooklyn and its welfare and health needs, including "Brooklyn Neighborhoods," by Herbert J. Ballon, containing detailed neighborhood-by-neighborhood assessments [no date, probably mid-1940s], and "Composition and Resources of Brooklyn," by Amy E. Krueger [1931], giving a summary of Brooklyn's "resources and of its composition that may be helpful to social workers."
    - Neighborhood Council: Correspondence, 1950-1954 (Box 27, Folder 7)
    - Neighborhood Council: Publications and Articles About (Box 27, Folder 8)
    - Neighborhood Resources: Reports and Statistics (Box 27, Folder 9)
  - Brownsville-Canarsie-East New York Coordinating Board, 1947-1973
    The Brownsville-Canarsie-East New York Coordinating Board was an administrative body formed to oversee the activities of the local health councils in these areas. Initially a unified body, it was later decentralized to allow greater autonomy in each separate neighborhood. The files in this subseries include correspondence regarding meetings of the Board, minutes, summaries of activities of the councils in Brownsville, Canarsie and East New York, and lists of members.
    - Annual Meeting, 1950 (Box 28, Folder 1)
    - Bylaws (Box 28, Folder 2)
    - Evaluation Committee, 1952 (Box 28, Folder 3)
    - Finances (Box 28, Folder 4)
    - Meetings, 1949-1952 (Box 28, Folder 5)
    - Related materials (Box 28, Folder 6)
    - Reports, 1949-1951 (Box 28, Folder 7)
  - Neighborhood council files, 1944-1957
    Alphabetical by neighborhood name (as it was designated in 1934-57), and then by agency name.
    BCSP did many neighborhood studies to assess health and welfare needs in varying parts of Brooklyn. To address these needs, BCSP acted as an advisor and a force in the creation of several neighborhood health and welfare councils in Brooklyn, including the Brownsville Health and Welfare Council, Canarsie Health Council, East New York Health Council, and the Fort Greene-Farragut Coordinating Committee (The files for Fort Greene were left in subseries 3.3, Programs: Group Work and Recreation, where they were found). BCSP also served as a consultant to Bedford-Stuyvesant Neighborhood Council, and the Eastern Parkway-Crown Heights Intergroup Council. These neighborhood councils were instrumental in setting up local day care centers, recreation centers, senior centers, and nursery schools. These files, which contain correspondence, reports, committee records, minutes, bylaws, surveys, pamphlets, and related material, document BCSP's participation in bringing health and welfare services to communities on a neighborhood level. Services in more than thirty Brooklyn neighborhoods are covered.
    Files for the councils directly affiliated with BCSP (Brownsville, Canarsie, East New York) are substantial, and include documentation on efforts to establish programs such as blood banks; classes on diabetes, nutrition, obesity, home nursing, and other topics; protection and establishment of neighborhood services including fire protection, sewers, and clean-ups; and local health and mental health clinics. The group on Bedford-Stuyvesant documents the Bedford-Stuyvesant Area Project on Juvenile Delinquency, the work of the Citizens Committee for a Municipal Hospital, the Maria Lawton Center for Older People, and the Bedford-Stuyvesant Community Center.
    - Brownsville: Canarsie: East NY Community Health Council (Box 28, Folder 8)
    - Bay Ridge: Bay Ridge Community Council (Box 28, Folder 9)
    - Bay Ridge: Miscellaneous (Box 28, Folder 10)
    - Bedford-Stuyvesant: Bedford-Stuyvesant Area Project (juvenile delinquency) (Box 28, Folder 11)
    - Bedford-Stuyvesant: Bedford-Stuyvesant Health Congress (Box 28, Folder 12)
    - Bedford-Stuyvesant: Child Care Committee (Box 28, Folder 13)
    - Bedford-Stuyvesant: Citizen's Committee for a Municipal Hospital (Box 28, Folder 14)
    - Bedford-Stuyvesant: Hospital: Press clippings (Box 28, Folder 15)